Pfeiffer, Fred; Papers apap139
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Fred Pfeiffer Papers
1937-2007
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap139
4.9 cubic ft.
The Fred Pfeiffer Papers document Pfeiffer's work with labor unions and activist organizations in the Albany, N.Y., area from the mid-1970s to 2007.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Fred Pfeiffer donated the papers to the M.E. Grenander Special Collections and Archives department in 2002 and 2015.
Biographical Sketch
Fred Pfeiffer has been involved in organized labor in the Albany, New York Capital District since the 1970s. He was a machinist at GE in Schenectady. He has worked with the Civil Service Employees Association (CSEA), International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers (IUE), American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), AFL-CIO, Solidarity Committee of the Capital District, Labor Committee for Safe Energy, Service Employees International Union (SEIU), the Campaign for a Livable Minimum Wage, and other national and local organizations. As a bargaining advisor, he helped to organize hospital workers, Capital District Off-Track Betting (OTB) workers, Albany Public Library employees, janitors in Albany, and others. He has also worked on behalf of various causes, notably NL Industries and the impact of nuclear power during the 1980s, and Latin American labor organizing and refugee programs, especially El Salvador, during the 1980s and early 1990s. Pfeiffer served as coordinator at the Capital District Worker Center for the Building Skills Project in the 2000s. Pfeiffer remains a lively local activist, most recently demonstrating with the Occupy Movement.
Scope and Contents
The Fred Pfeiffer Papers contain records resulting from his work with various unions and activist organizations in the Albany, NY area, as well as a collection of union-related materials such as contracts, newsletters, and publications that have historical significance. While all of the series include material directly related to Pfeiffer's work, Series 1 and 2 consist of the most substantial amount of Pfeiffer-related papers. In particular, please see the CSEA and SEIU folders in Series 1 and in the Labor Committee for Safe Energy folder in Series 2. Series 2 contains information on nuclear energy activism and organized labor's engagement with energy issues, mostly during the 1980s. Series 3 relates to labor organizing in Latin America and internationally during the 1980s and 1990s. Series 3 also includes anti-NAFTA, anti-GATT, and anti-WTO materials. Series 4 is a diverse set of published documents and artifacts (mostly buttons and pins) related to labor organizations, conventions, government reports, protests and marches.
Separated Materials
Archivists transfered a monograph An Organizer's Notebook on Public Utilities and Energy, to the book division of Special Collections. The catalogue record is now included in the University Libraries Catalog.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Union and Community Organizing, 1973-2007, Undated
Series 2 - Energy and Labor, 1962-1996, Undated
Series 3 - International Labor Organizing, 1980-1994, Undated
Series 4 - Subject Files, 1937-1996, Undated
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Conservation and the Environment; Labor Unions--Organizing--New York(State); Labor Unions--Organizing--Latin America; Nuclear Energy--New York (State)--Public Opinion; New York (State)--Social conditions; Clippings; Minutes; Files by subject; Newsletters; Artifacts; Official reports; Pfeiffer, Fred; Civil Service Employees Association (N.Y.); AFL-CIO; Service Employees International Union; AFSCME; Solidarity Committee of the Capital District
- Union and Community Organizing, 1973-2007; Undated; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series is composed of meeting minutes, personal notes, correspondence, newsletters, event plans, agendas, and other materials related to organizing efforts or union business. Fred Pfeiffer worked with CSEA, SEIU, AFSCME, AFL-CIO, the Solidarity Committee of the Capital District, the Campaign for a Livable Minimum Wage, and the Capital District Workers Center. The largest amount of material is from his experiences with AFSCME, CSEA and SEIU.
  - CSEA Local 445, Eleanor Roosevelt Developmental Services, Meeting Minutes, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - CSEA Local 445, Eleanor Roosevelt Developmental Services, Newsletter, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - CSEA Local 445, Eleanor Roosevelt Developmental Services, By-Laws and Budget, 1976-1979; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - CSEA Local 445, Eleanor Roosevelt Developmental Services, Disciplinary Hearing, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ENYCOSH and Silkwood Project (1 of 2), 1977-1983; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - ENYCOSH and Silkwood Project (2 of 2), 1977-1983; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Glass Bottle Blower Association, 1979; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Solidarity Committee of the Capital District, Workers in Unions Film Series Posters, 1984; Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 1)
  - Solidarity Committee of the Capital District, 1984; 1986; 1991; 1994-1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - IUE, Brushworker, 1985-1986; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - SEIU, Local 200-D (1 of 2), 1986-2000; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - SEIU, Local 200-D (2 of 2), 1986-2000; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - SEIU, D Connect Newsletter, 1987-1989; 1995; 1998-2000; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - AFSCME, Council 66 News, 1991-1994 (Oversized 2, Folder 2)
  - AFSCME, General Electric Taxes in Schenectady (1 of 2), 1991-1994; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - AFSCME, General Electric Taxes in Schenectady (2 of 2), 1991-1994; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - AFSCME, Council 66, 1991-1997; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - AFSCME, Regional Reports, 1992-1993; Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Albany Public Library Workers, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Capital District Off-Track Betting Workers, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Campaign for a Livable Minimum Wage (1 of 2), 1994-1997; 1999; Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Campaign for a Livable Minimum Wage (2 of 2), 1994-1997; 1999; Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Graduate Students, 1994; 1996-1997; Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - AFL-CIO Poster about Governor Pataki's Budget, ca. 1996 (Oversized 2, Folder 3)
  - Workers' Rights Board, 1997; 2005 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - SEIU, Local 200-D, Minutes, Reports and Notes (1 of 3), 1998-2001 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - SEIU, Local 200-D, Minutes, Reports and Notes (2 of 3), 1998-2001 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - SEIU, Local 200-D, Minutes, Reports and Notes (3 of 3), 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - SEIU, 1199, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Capital District Worker Center, 2004-2007 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Fred Pfeiffer's Resume, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - SEIU, Local 200-D, T-Shirts, Undated (Oversized 1, Folder 1)
- Energy and Labor, 1962-1996; Undated; 2
  This series' biggest concentration of materials spans the late 1970s to the mid-1980s and contains Fred Pfeiffer's founding and organizing work with the Labor Committee for Safe Energy. The clippings, notes, publications, pamphlets, reports, official government documents, and flyers related to NL Industries are extensive. The folders for the PSC/CUB and GE PEP include materials related to Pfeiffer's work with the International Union of Electrical Workers (IUE) Local 301. There are also several publications relating to the Three Mile Island partial meltdown accident. Of interesting note is folder 5 in Box 1 which includes a stapled together package of various newspaper articles including one on a KKK recruitment drive outside the Seabrook Nuclear Power Plant.
  - Pro-Nuke Unionism, 1962; 1977-1981; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Peace and Conversion, 1977-1993; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Uranium Mining, Australian Metal Workers, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Powerline", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Assorted Nuclear Energy Related Materials, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Labor Committee for Safe Energy (1 of 2), 1978-1983; 1986; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Labor Committee for Safe Energy (2 of 2), 1978-1983; 1986; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - NL Industries (1 of 3), 1978-1984; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - NL Industries (2 of 3), 1978-1984; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - NL Industries (3 of 3), 1978-1984; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Atoms at Work Around the World, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Three Mile Island, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Capital District Anti-Nuclear Alliance (CDANA) (1 of 4), 1979-1982; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Capital District Anti-Nuclear Alliance (CDANA) (2 of 4), 1979-1982; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Capital District Anti-Nuclear Alliance (CDANA) (3 of 4), 1979-1982; Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Capital District Anti-Nuclear Alliance (CDANA) (4 of 4), 1979-1982; Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - KITE, 1980 (Oversized 2, Folder 4)
  - General Electric, PEP, IUE, 1980-1993; Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Powerline", 1981 (Oversized 2, Folder 5)
  - Sierra Club, 1981; Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Public Services Commission (PSC) and Citizens Utility Board (CUB), 1981-1996; Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - IUE, Fuel Adjustment Clause, PSC Case #27741, 1982-1983; Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Groundswell", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - South Korea and Nuclear Plant Project, 1986; Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Film Order Forms, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Toxic Crisis, Time for Action", Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Earthroots Newspaper, "Northern Rights Southern Light", 1991 (Oversized 2, Folder 6)
  - "Three Mile Island: One Year Later, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 7)
- International Labor Organizing, 1980-1994; Undated; 3
  This series contains materials related to labor organizing in Latin America, South America, and the Caribbean, with a strong collection of correspondence, clippings, government documents, and organizing materials about El Salvador. The series also contains materials on South Africa, the Philippines, and the Far East. The folder on Free Trade contains records on local organizing efforts and anti-NAFTA, anti-GATT, and anti-WTO materials. Pfeiffer was engaged with international labor organizing through unions and activist organizations in the Albany area. The Chilean folder is almost entirely in Spanish. A United Ireland newsletter from the Irish Republican Clubs in Albany, New York is found in Folder 11.
  - Cruzada Nacional de Alfabetizacion, Nicaragua Stickers, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Military Intervention Threat in Far East, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - El Salvador, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Central American Briefing Book, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Guatemala, Coca-Cola Display, 1984; 1986; 1990-1991; 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Latin America, General, 1984; 1986; 1991; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Guatemala, General, 1984; 1990; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Andean Focus, 1985-1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Labor Action, A Call To Action, Newsletters, 1985-1994; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Grenada, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Nicaragua, 1987; 1991; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - El Salvador, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mexico, 1988; 1991; 1993; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chile, 1989; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Puerto Rico, 1989-1990; 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - El Salvador, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Free Trade (1 of 3), 1990-1994; Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Free Trade (2 of 3), 1990-1994; Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Free Trade (3 of 3), 1990-1994; Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - AFL-CIO News, "Jobs Exported To Mexico", 1991 (Oversized 2, Folder 8)
  - El Salvador, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Haiti, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Boycott Salvadoran Coffee" Poster, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 9)
  - Cuba, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - El Salvador (1 of 2), Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - El Salvador (2 of 2), Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Guyana, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Philippines, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - South Africa, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Subject Files, 1937-1996; Undated; 4
  This series includes a box of pins and buttons related to political campaigns (including ones for Democratic U.S. Presidential candidates), union programs, protests, and marches. Most of the buttons are undated, although some are stamped with the date of the election or related special event. There is a 1993 The Catholic Worker about the death of Cezar Chavez, Guatemalan refugee crisis and GATT. There also is a collection of contracts and workers' agreements, historically significant publications from national AFL-CIO meetings, and U.S. Senate Reports related to organized labor. Two NACLA's Latin America and Empire Report about President Richard Nixon are included here.
  - Violations of Free Speech and Rights of Labor "Harlan County," U.S. Senate Report, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Textile Workers Union of America, Agreement, Constitution, Ethical Practices, 1946; 1953; 1957-1958; 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AFL, Proceedings of the 74th Convention, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - AFL-CIO, Draft Constitution, IUD Digest, 1955; 1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hudson Valley Area Joint Board Sealy Mattress Strike by TWUA, Schenectady, Albany, Buffalo, 1960s (Film 1)
  - Worker Alienation, U.S. Senate Report, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - NACLA's Latin America and Empire Report, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Association of Bridge, Structural, and Ornamental Iron Workers, Shopmens Local 534, Agreement, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Glass Bottle Blower's Association, Local By-Laws, Contract, Constitution, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "The Truth About the Crisis in Steel", 1977
  - United Cement, Lime and Gypsum Workers International Union, Agreement, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - United Mine Workers Association, Bargaining Bulletin, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Public Employee Federation, Resolutions, Bulletin, 1981; 1995; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Brushworkers Union, Contract, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Report to Governor and Legislators on Garment Manufacturing Industry and Industrial Homework, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "America Invades Grenada," The Village Voice, 1983 (Oversized 2, Folder 10)
  - U.S. Wages, 1983; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Pins and Buttons from Various Demonstrations, Labor Unions, and Political Campaigns, 1983-1996; Undated (Artifact-box 1)
  - A Report on the Plight of the Collective Bargaining System, NYS Assembly Report, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Focus on Central America, Alert!", 1985 (Oversized 2, Folder 11)
  - Metroland, 1987 (Oversized 2, Folder 12)
  - Glass, Molders, Pottery, Plastics and Allied Workers International Union, Constitution, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Green Island Plant, "65 Years of Pride", 1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Chile Vencera", 1989 (Oversized 2, Folder 13)
  - IUE Local 318, Agreement, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - James Joseph Roti, Award of Merit Dinner, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Official New York State Martin Luther King Jr., Holiday March to Capitol, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Free Trade Newspaper Articles, 1991; 1993 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - New York State Senator Franz S. Leichter, Reports on Corporate Welfare, 1991; 1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Smith Corona Corp., Cortland Plant Closing, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Catholic Worker, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Farmers' Rights, 1993; Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - SENSES, Counterbudget, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Kate Bronfenbrenner Union Organizing Reports, 1995; Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - American Postal Workers Union, "The Albany Post", 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - AFSCEME Patch, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - AFSCEME Stickers Supporting Bill Clinton, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "Blueprint for a Working America", Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Coalition for Public Higher Education Sticker Supporting SUNY, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Lock Haven and the Dream Deferred, Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Stickers Protesting USA Today/Gannet Subsidiary, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Trade Crisis, Time for Action", Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)